<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A representation of the present affairs and interests of the most considerable parts of Europe, more especially of those of the Netherlands as they now stand, in the beginning of the year 1677. Laid open in a letter from Holland. By a lover of truth and peace.</title>
            <author>Lover of truth and peace.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1677</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 74 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57045</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1106</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206033</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99825385</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99825385</idno>
            <idno type="VID">29767</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57045)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 29767)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2056:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A representation of the present affairs and interests of the most considerable parts of Europe, more especially of those of the Netherlands as they now stand, in the beginning of the year 1677. Laid open in a letter from Holland. By a lover of truth and peace.</title>
                  <author>Lover of truth and peace.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Dom. 1676/7 [i.e. 1677]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dutch War, 1672-1678 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Europe --  History --  1648-1715 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:29767:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A REPRESENTATION of the preſent Affairs and Intereſts of the moſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable parts of EUROPE, <hi>more eſpecially of thoſe of the</hi> NETHERLANDS: As they now ſtand, in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the year 1677.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laid open in a Letter from Holland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By a Lover of Truth and Peace.</p>
            <p>Anno Dom. 1676/7.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:29767:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:29767:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>R,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Upon ſome ſerious Conſiderations late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly had by us both touching the great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion and Calamities of ſundry parts of <hi>Europe,</hi> &amp; particularly of <hi>the Netherlands,</hi> you were pleaſed to put ſuch a value upon my judgement (beyond it's deſerts) as to aſk my opinion of the ſource &amp; progreſs of thoſe Evills, together with my Advice concerning ſuch Remedies as might reſtore the Lands to their former reſt, and the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants to their ancient foelicity and ſafety.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>,</hi> This was not the work of One day, nor is it now poſſible in one Letter to comprehend ſo ample a Relation, or diſcuſſion of thoſe things wherein ſo many, ſo grand, and ſo various cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances occur; Neither have I now the leiſure to reduce them into ſuch a diſtinct Method as you might expect. But according to the ſeverall diſcourſes I daily am accoſted with, &amp; the obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions I have made of perſons and paſſages, I ſhall give you a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall view of our Maladies; the idea whereof may haply ſomwhat move your compaſſion, though it cannot have ſo great an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence upon the affections of your Countreymen, as upon thoſe on this ſide the water, who have born and are yet likely to bear the heat and burden of a ſad and dolefull day: And as for an <hi>Eſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapius</hi> to heal theſe dreadfull wounds, ſomthing we ſhall aſſay, though rather wiſh than hope for ſuch an Expedient; unleſs you in <hi>England,</hi> ſenſible, that when your Neighbours houſes are on fire, apprehending your own cannot long eſcape, ſhall be moved to add a helping hand ere it be too late.</p>
            <p>Now, <hi>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>,</hi> for the better anſwering of your expectation, ere I give you my own Obſervations, I judge it not amiſs to propoſe to you the ſeverall ſentiments of the 2. great Heads of the preſent contending parties: and ſith Our ears are daily filled with the noiſe of their loud boaſtings, high pretences and mutuall calumnia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, I take the Freedom to exerciſe your patience with an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:29767:3"/>of their own Rhodomantado's; which I cannot better do than by perſonating One of each Nation.</p>
            <p>I shall firſt introduce the <hi>Frenchman:</hi> who would perſwade us to a belief that <hi>his King</hi> is the onely qualified Prince of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to become <hi>Emperour,</hi> not onely of <hi>Europe,</hi> but of the world. And thus you may hear him Flourishing over the enco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miums of his King, Countrey and Cauſe.</p>
            <q>
               <p>In the firſt place <hi>(ſaith the Monſieur)</hi> I ſay, That my Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Lord and Maſter, <hi>His moſt Chriſtian Majeſtie</hi> is every way qualified for the Soveraign Imperial Dignity and Charge: I shall begin with his <hi>Perſon,</hi> which no man can deny to be the moſt graceful of all the Princes on earth: his mind yet more richly adorned with all the graces and tranſcendent Excellencies and Endowments which may become a Prince. Had he lived in ſome days, no doubt, he would have been reckoned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Gods. He came into the world with a wonder, therefore was he named <hi>Dieu done, Gods gift:</hi> and being ſo mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culouſly given beyond all expectation, 't is a ſign he came to do ſome grand work; he being prophecied of by many, as if he were to begin or ſet up the Fifth Monarchy: and to me this ſeems evident: for when you shall well weigh what great and glorious things he hath don, in raiſing the Monarchy of <hi>France</hi> to that degree of height as hath never yet hitherto been known, adding thereto ſo many great Conqueſts, and that in very few years, to the aſtonishment of all the Princes in <hi>Europe,</hi> and the admiration of the <hi>Great Turk,</hi> who, you find, ſends an Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour to treat his <hi>Chriſtian Majeſtie</hi> with the Title of <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour,</hi> which never formerly was given to any <hi>King of France</hi> ſince <hi>Charle Main's</hi> time; and when you shall truly conſider the great power of <hi>my King</hi> at Land and Sea, certainly you muſt yield him to be the moſt potent of all the Princes of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom: He is able to bring two hundred thouſand men to fight, and yet not take three men out of a Parish: for 'tis un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniable, that in <hi>France</hi> alone and it's limits, leaving out <hi>Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain, Burgundy, French County and Alſatia,</hi> he hath within the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:29767:3"/>
                  <hi>French Monarchy,</hi> one hundred and thirty three thouſand Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishes. But, before I ſpeak of his Riches and vaſt Dominions, I ought to mention ſomthing of the vertues of his mind, which are ſo numerous, that certainly never have ſo many met toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in any Prince in our modern times: he is all <hi>bon Air</hi> and curteous beyond expreſſion: and yet in labours, vigilan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and hazards, who ever more ſedulous? And what Prince ever out-did him in diſtributions of juſtice and rewards to the meritorious? What encouragements doth he give to the Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuoſo's? What penſions are given to the widows and orphans of the brave <hi>English</hi> and other Nations that have ſerv'd him well? Nor can his own Subjects complain of miſſing their reward when they deſerve it. And this his glorious Example hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten an imitation in his Subjects: What numbers of brave Generalls and skilfull Officers is <hi>France</hi> plentifully furnished with? What a diſciplined Army is that of the French? none in in the world to be compared to them. And if you take notice of the Riches of <hi>my King</hi> in the Number of his Subjects, then you will grant, he exceeds all <hi>Europe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Charle Magne</hi> was of opinion that <hi>France,</hi> for it's ſituation, was the moſt convenient and commodious Countrey of all <hi>Europe</hi> for making the Reſidential ſeat for the <hi>Emperour:</hi> and <hi>Charle le Magne</hi> had made it ſo, had not theſe two conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions overſwayed, <hi>viz.</hi> (1.) That the <hi>German</hi> Princes and their Countreys might ſo have taken the opportunity of returning back to their <hi>Heatheniſm,</hi> to which they were very inclining. (2) Sith at the time of his diſpoſall of his poſſeſſions amongſt his Sons, <hi>France</hi> (now ſo called) was under ſeverall Princes and Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates, which <hi>Charle Magne</hi> in juſtice could not turn out of their lawfull rights, as <hi>Languedock, Provence, Britain, Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandy</hi> and ſeverall other Provinces: But now theſe, and divers more, as <hi>Lorain, Alſatia, French County, Burgundy</hi> and a great part of the <hi>Netherlands</hi> are of later years added and laid to the <hi>Monarchy of France.</hi> I am of opinion, that if <hi>my King</hi> should
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:29767:4"/>joyn with <hi>his Majeſtie of Great Britain,</hi> they Two might divide the world between them; the One to be <hi>Emperour</hi> at Land, the Other at Sea: and 'tis both reaſonable and naturall it should be ſo: for <hi>We</hi> and the <hi>English</hi> are So mixt in bloud, and our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanguinity ſuch that We are One People: <hi>The English</hi> have been ſeverall ages in France; as may be ſeen by the ſtately Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es and other Fabricks they built, whilſt in <hi>France:</hi> Then the <hi>Normans</hi> poſſeſſed and governed <hi>England;</hi> as may appear by the Laws written in the <hi>French</hi> tongue, and yet remaining in practice to this very day: ſo that we are an <hi>English-French,</hi> and they a <hi>French-English.</hi> But if the <hi>King of Great Britain</hi> will not joyn with nor aſſiſt <hi>my King,</hi> yet he muſt, notwithſtanding that, be <hi>Emperour;</hi> all things tend to it. Is not <hi>Paris</hi> now become like <hi>Rome</hi> in old time, who gave Laws and taught Manners to the whole world? As in thoſe days all Nations learned <hi>Latin,</hi> that thereby they might underſtand the Civilities, Laws and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation of <hi>the Romans:</hi> So now, Do not all Nations learn French? Do not you ſend all your choice and Nobleſt-born Princes, Gentry, and richeſt Merchants Sons to our <hi>Academies</hi> in <hi>Paris?</hi> Do not We impoſe on you all the Modes of <hi>France?</hi> Take but a view of all <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> and you will find, That there's not ſo much as a little <hi>German Prince</hi> but he muſt have a <hi>Frenchman</hi> for his Barber, <hi>Valet de chambre,</hi> or Lackey; and one of theſe often makes a Governour for the young Prince, and a moſt Excellent Privy Councellour. Somtimes I have known a Prince that hath kept himſelf undreſt ſix days, expecting with great impatience his perwiggs and feathers, and other gallan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries out of <hi>France.</hi> Travel into what parts you pleaſe where there is a Court, as in <hi>Rome,</hi> and even in <hi>Madrid</hi> itſelf, there you shall find every Prince and Gentilman hath <hi>a Frenchman</hi> to teach him how to dreſs himſelf, yea, and how to eat with a <hi>bon mein.</hi> Go no farther than to <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> or more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to <hi>the Hagh,</hi> where you may obſerve all to be turn'd perfect <hi>Monſieurs:</hi> and in <hi>Amſterdam</hi> the <hi>old Hollander</hi> is ſo changed,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:29767:4"/>that there is ſcarce ſuch a Creature to be found: there is not a rich Merchants daughter there that will admit of a <hi>Bezuca,</hi> much leſs go to Church to be married untill she hath her Modes, Curls for her head, her Tower &amp;c. from <hi>France,</hi> or at leſt, buy the ſame of a <hi>French Madam,</hi> who, with the help of a <hi>French Dancing-Maſter,</hi> ſet's Mrs. Brides Locks, teacheth her the Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and Coupé, and then perſwades her, She is the moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat Madam <hi>a la mode</hi> in the Town; giving as an adviſe, that nothing but a <hi>French Feile de Chambre</hi> can preſerve the Dreſs and <hi>bon meyn</hi> they have left her in. Thus are <hi>We French</hi> the Fashion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers and School of Manners and good breeding for the Univerſe. Beſides all this, All <hi>Europe</hi> and Other parts of the world are beholden to us for Invention: Our <hi>King</hi> hath eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished in <hi>Paris</hi> 2 Colledges, One for a Royal Society of <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuoſo's,</hi> the Other called <hi>Bon Eſprit.</hi> In a word, <hi>France</hi> furnish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the world with more numbers of Good Writers, Fighters, and Men <hi>Onet &amp; bein a juſte,</hi> than all Chriſtendom beſides.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gentilmen,</hi> I ſuppoſe you know, I am a Son of <hi>the Church of Rome;</hi> yet I wish from my very heart, that <hi>the Dolphine</hi> were crowned <hi>King of the Romans:</hi> For my part, I wish that old <hi>Holy man</hi> and all the Fops about him were removed to ſome other place; and ſo make room for a Brave <hi>Emperour,</hi> ſuch as <hi>my King</hi> or <hi>the Dolphine</hi> would make: but if he muſt needs live in <hi>Rome,</hi> let him be content to live in <hi>St. Iohn de Lateran,</hi> as in old time: Five hundred piſtols a year is more than any honeſt <hi>Bishop</hi> in the world ought to ſpend, if he live like a true Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd, and uſeth onely his Croſiers Staff. <hi>Murblew,</hi> Since the Bishops traverſed the ſword over the Croſiers Staff in their Arms, the Churchmen become Fighters and Executioners of Civil Juſtice; which, to my judgement, is quite contrary to <hi>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Pauls</hi> words, <hi>Let not a Bishop be a ſtriker.</hi> My Opinion is, That if the thirty five Millions of Livres which the <hi>Pope</hi> and his Idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pack or lazy Drones devour, were employed in the maintaining of a brave army againſt <hi>the Turk,</hi> it might be better ſpent. You
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:29767:5"/>shall ſee in ſome few years, if <hi>my Maſter</hi> be not <hi>Emperour,</hi> that the <hi>Turk</hi> will make bold to give <hi>his Holineſs</hi> a Viſit from <hi>Candia.</hi> And, on the contrary, if <hi>my King</hi> be <hi>Emperour,</hi> you will ſee the <hi>Flower-de Luces</hi> placed in the room of the 3. <hi>Half-Moons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If Any think I have been too ſatyrical touching the <hi>Pope</hi> and his <hi>Cardinals,</hi> and ſpoken too irreverently of them, ſith, Some of thoſe <hi>Bishops of Rome</hi> have been good men, as <hi>Sixtus Quintus</hi> a Gentleman eminent both for learning and Religion, the like whereof may be ſaid of that devout man <hi>Cardinal Bona</hi> lately dead, yet living in his highly eſteemed works; as alſo that <hi>Pope Alexander the</hi> VII. was a <hi>Gentleman</hi> &amp;c. Yet for all that, Know, that I handle that ſort of men very modeſtly: I could blacken the <hi>See of Rome,</hi> in this Diſcourſe, at another rate, if I were not a Child of that <hi>Church.</hi> I could tell of ſeverall <hi>Popes.</hi> who lived and died <hi>Heathens;</hi> Some of their bodies having been taken up and burned, as is for truth received, after their tenents were found in their Cloſets: neither, have I painted out the Lives of Some <hi>Cardinals</hi> in my days; thoſe are things ſo well known by them who live among them, that 'tis needleſs here to repeat what's in every vulgar mouth. In short, Let me ſay over again, If <hi>the Pope</hi> and his Crew, who, poſſeſs <hi>Rome,</hi> do continue ſo to rule, and that <hi>Italy</hi> be thus governed, moſt by the <hi>Church,</hi> then, ſay I, <hi>the Turk</hi> or any Other Neighbour may take the Countrey from them: (Let it be remembred what <hi>my King</hi> did at <hi>Avignion:</hi>) for their Countrey is half depopu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated; which is occaſioned by 3. things: <hi>Firſt,</hi> by making ſuch vaſt numbers of <hi>Eunuchs. Secondly,</hi> by practiſing the ſin of <hi>Sodom</hi> ſo much as they do: for it is moſt certainly true, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thouſands of <hi>Italians</hi> perfectly hate the Female Sex. <hi>Laſtly,</hi> by the innumerable Company of <hi>Monaſteries</hi> and <hi>Nunneries;</hi> in which may be modeſtly accounted two hundred thouſand Nuns; the which, if lawfully employed in generation-work, might produce great numbers of uſefull Creatures: whereas now, on the contrary, both <hi>Monks, Friers</hi> and <hi>Nuns</hi> are forced
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:29767:5"/>to make uſe of all their skil and arts to deſtroy Gods image by them made in ſecret, and all to hide the ſcandal of being ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted breakers of the unwarrantable oaths and vows they make to obſerve their Founders Maximes or Rules of their Order.</p>
               <p>To conclude my Diſcourſe, I will onely ſay this One thing more touching the qualification of My <hi>Maſter</hi> to become <hi>Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour,</hi> rather than any Other King: and that is, <hi>His moſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Toleration of Liberty of Conſcience</hi> in all his Dominions and Territories. In <hi>France</hi> you find ſeverall <hi>Proteſtant-Univerſities,</hi> and great numbers of Temples and Churches for the <hi>Proteſtant-Worship.</hi> Conſider but what abundance of <hi>French-Miniſters</hi> are ſent thence to ſerve the <hi>Proteſtant-Churches</hi> abroad, as under that one Government of the <hi>States of the United Provinees;</hi> where may be reckoned about <hi>Fiftie French Miniſters;</hi> beſides what are in <hi>England, Germany</hi> and other Countreys. Our <hi>Doctors of the Sorbon</hi> are not ſuch Fools as to maintain or nourish an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition;</hi> No: Nor will <hi>Our King</hi> refuſe the good ſervice of the <hi>Proteſtants:</hi> On the contrary, He makes them <hi>Preſidents of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> and <hi>Secretaries of State</hi> in ſeverall Provinces, alſo <hi>Generals</hi> and other <hi>Officers</hi> in his <hi>Armies,</hi> according to their merit. Whereas on the other hand, <hi>the Houſe of Auſtria</hi> will permit no man to have preferment in the <hi>Emperours</hi> or <hi>King of Spains Courts,</hi> unleſs he firſt become a <hi>Papiſt.</hi> And if you well weigh the horrid, hellish and abſolutely unwarrantable practices of the <hi>Spanish In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition,</hi> then will you with me confeſs, that moſt of the Evils that have befallen Chriſtendom, have had their Riſe from that Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolical Court of <hi>Inquiſition:</hi> it makes more <hi>Iews</hi> in <hi>Spain, Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal,</hi> and <hi>Italy,</hi> than would be; occaſioned from the worſe than Barbarous cruelty practiſed by the Lords of that <hi>Inquiſition:</hi> for, ſay the <hi>Iews,</hi> as you pretend, your <hi>Ieſus</hi> was filled with bowels of Love and compaſſion; yet to the contrary, you practiſe worſe cruelties than ever did, any <hi>Pagan.</hi> I pray alſo, what was the Cauſe of the <hi>Netherlanders</hi> Revolt? And what were the deſigns of the <hi>Spanjards</hi> againſt <hi>Queen Elizabeth</hi> in 88? and from whom
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:29767:6"/>came that wicked Plot or <hi>Gun-powder-Treaſon</hi> in <hi>King Iames</hi> his days? you will anſwer me, theſe were hatch'd in <hi>Spain</hi> by the <hi>Spanish Inquiſition.</hi> &amp; if you caſt your eye upon our preſent Age, you will find <hi>Meſsina</hi> revolting from the ſame Cauſe; at leſt from the ill Government of <hi>the Houſe of Auſtria;</hi> which if a man take a view of, either in the Kingdom of <hi>Naples, Milain, Sicily</hi> or in <hi>Spain</hi> itſelf, he will behold ſuch diſorder in the civil Government, that it is a miracle how that Monarchy hath ſo long continued.</p>
               <p>I thought to have ſaid ſomthing touching <hi>my King</hi> his being lineally deſcended from <hi>Charlemagne:</hi> But that I shall refer to another opportunity: and ſo put a Period to what I have to ſay upon this high and eminent and juſt Deſign.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Thus have you the <hi>Frenchmans</hi> Pretences, with the Rhetorick uſed to beget a belief and approbation of the righteous and neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry grounds of their high Undertakings.</p>
            <p>Now pleaſe to admit the <hi>Spanjard</hi> to be heard in his ſober Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication: and permit me to bring him alſo upon the Stage, mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing anſwer to what with patience hath been born out of the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of the vapouring <hi>Frenchman.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus the <hi>Don</hi> begins:</p>
            <q>
               <p>I acknowledge that the <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur,</hi> like a true-born <hi>Frenchman,</hi> hath made a large <hi>Bravado:</hi> and yet if all were true he hath aſſerted, I doubt not but to give you greater Arguments and Demonſtrations to prove that No one Familie in <hi>Europe</hi> or in the whole world is of that conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration as is <hi>my Kings Familie:</hi> yea, I do affirm, that No two Kings in Chriſtendom have half the ſtrength in numbers of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and quantities of Countreys and Provinces as are under the Command of <hi>my Maſters Familie.</hi> 'Twere but time vainly ſpent to entertain you with anſwering the <hi>Monſieur</hi> to that wherein he would impoſe upon us a belief that <hi>his King</hi> is line<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally deſcended from <hi>Charlemagne:</hi> For your Conviction, 'tis but onely caſting your eye upon that piece of Treaſon practiſed by a <hi>Iacobin-Frier</hi> on the <hi>Houſe of Valois,</hi> for the bringing in this <hi>Houſe of Bourbon;</hi> of which this <hi>Lewis the 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi>.</hi> is the Third.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:29767:6"/>
               <p>But moſt apparent it is, that the <hi>Houſe of Auſtria</hi> is a true branch of the <hi>Charlovinyans;</hi> as is evident from ſeverall Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians. Touching therefore the Right or Title that either the <hi>Houſe of Bourbon</hi> or <hi>Auſtria</hi> hath to the <hi>Imperial Crown,</hi> I shall not proceed to diſcourſe, becauſe 'tis ſo well known where the Right is, that this is the firſt time I ever heard it brought in quaeſtion.</p>
               <p>But I shall go on to show you why the <hi>Imperial Crown</hi> ought to remain in <hi>the Houſe of Auſtria.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> Do but conſider what vaſt numbers of Kingdoms, Dukedoms and Segniories <hi>the Houſe of Auſtria</hi> doth poſſeſs: and by that you may judge how much they exceed in Subjects, Riches, and quantity of Land: I will name ſome of their Poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, <hi>viz.</hi> the Kingdoms of <hi>Leon, Aragon, Catalonia, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varre, Naples, Granada, Myrcia, Valentia, Caſtilia, Biſcaia, Galicia, Algarle, Cicilia, Hungary, Bohemia, the Dukedoms of Burgondy, Milain, Auſtria;</hi> part of the <hi>Netherlands:</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides all theſe, many <hi>Isles</hi> in <hi>Europe</hi> and <hi>Africa,</hi> as <hi>Tenerif, the Canary Islands</hi> &amp;c. Beyond all which, if a view could be taken of the large extent of thoſe grand Kingdoms and Provinces, Iſles and various Territories they have in the <hi>Eaſt and Weſt-In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,</hi> as their Patrimony left them by <hi>St. Peter,</hi> then might you truly grant that to be a reality which hath ſo long been aſſerted, <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>the Sun always shines on their Dominions.</hi> But further, if you shall make a compariſon between the Riches, Traffick, and Merchandiſe of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> with that of <hi>France;</hi> 'twill be evident to you, the One is but a Pedlers Shop, the Other a Rich Magazin of gold, ſilver, pearls, ſilks, and ſpice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. For a Demonſtration hereof, Do but ask the <hi>Englishman,</hi> what Kind of Merchandizes the <hi>French</hi> bring over into <hi>England,</hi> and what ſort of Trumperie and Pedling-Merchants <hi>the French</hi> there be: The beſt Merchandiſe <hi>the French</hi> furnish other parts of the world with, except ſome ſalt and wine, is little better than Bables and Toys, when at the ſame time We <hi>Spanjards</hi> ſend
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:29767:7"/>great quantities of Bullion, and rich Silks, fine Wool &amp;c. And as for the <hi>French</hi> Traders in <hi>England,</hi> Do but obſerve them, and you will find them, for the moſt part, Barbers, Taylors, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wigg-makers, John Potages, and a ſort of Vermin, that onely live ſo long in <hi>England</hi> untill they have ſwell'd themſelvs full with the riches of that Land; and then they fly to France again, and diſgorge that Riches on ſome few acres of Land; by which means, after a year or two, ſtarts up, mushrom-like, <hi>Monſ<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Marqués de Chandellé, de bel Gantelet</hi> or <hi>Marq. de peigne, Marq. de Valet &amp;c.</hi> and this great grievance bring the <hi>French</hi> to all Nations where e're they come, that they marry ſome <hi>Fille de Chambre,</hi> and they two, dwelling in Chambers, paying no cuſtom or duties, make children together; and moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly the Wives and Brats are left to the Parish to maintain; nay, yet further, how is every Priſon, yea and Hoſpital fill'd with them in England? yea and the gallows too ſomtimes, witneſs the <hi>Frenchman</hi> that ſet <hi>London</hi> on fire, and <hi>the Monſieur</hi> that kill'd <hi>his Maſter.</hi> When to the contrary of this, I dare be bold to affirm it, that there are in all <hi>London</hi> ſcarce two <hi>Spanish</hi> Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, Taylors, or Mechanick Handicrafts-Tradeſmen: all being great and able Merchants or Bankers.</p>
               <p>Now whereas the <hi>Frenchman</hi> makes a ſemblance of Religion, and giving freedom to Religious people; Let All men judge of this, who do but lend their ears to the moſt deplorable ſtories of their cruelties in deſtroying ſo many hundred Towns and thouſands of poor People in the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> in <hi>Alſatia, Twee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brugge</hi> and the circumjacent parts; ſuch dreadfull burnings, rov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, plunderings and tyranny exerciſed on an innocent peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple hath not been paralelled in a whole age, as they have now committed within theſe 2 laſt Months of <hi>Ianuary</hi> and <hi>February.</hi> And whereas <hi>the Monſieur</hi> ſaith, that if <hi>his Maſter</hi> were <hi>Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour,</hi> he would thruſt the <hi>Grand Seigneur</hi> out at a farther diſtance from <hi>Italy</hi> and <hi>Hungary,</hi> I believe 't is no hard matter to prove that it is <hi>He</hi> that hath invited him into <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> to make
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:29767:7"/>diverſion, whilſt he practiſeth his deſigns upon <hi>the Emperour.</hi> and 't is moſt certain, that it was the <hi>French</hi> alone that widened the breach in <hi>Germany</hi> between the <hi>Emperour</hi> and <hi>the Princes</hi> in the laſt Civil War. <hi>The Frenchman</hi> is not ashamed to boaſt of his Kings Actions about <hi>Avignion;</hi> alſo telling us, that there is no uſe for the <hi>Pope,</hi> ſith the <hi>Sorbon-Doctors</hi> can do all as well: but as to the <hi>French Kings</hi> manner of treating the <hi>Pope</hi> at <hi>Avig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,</hi> and his rendring the <hi>Pope</hi> uſeleſs, let every true Catholick judge how religiouſly thoſe things look.</p>
               <p>For a Concluſion, I shall onely put <hi>the Monſieur</hi> to a change of his countenance, and, it may be, of his ambition alſo, when I shall advertiſe him of the great diſappointment of his <hi>Grand Maſters</hi> expectations touching his hopes of inteſtin troubles in <hi>Spain;</hi> the thoughts whereof do now wholly vanish, upon the peaceable entrance of that Illuſtrious Prince <hi>Don Iohn</hi> into <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drid,</hi> and the right underſtanding between <hi>the King my Maſter</hi> and him; together with his preſent capacity of relieving <hi>Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonia,</hi> and, perhaps, giving a viſit to the King of France, where he will ſcarce be welcome: From him doubtleſs, I mean, that honeſt &amp; heroick <hi>Spanjard, Don Iohn,</hi> all men of ſober judgements expect both good and great things, ſuch as may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the grandour of his perſon, and integrity of his princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Thus have you an account of the Eſſays made by the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions of theſe aſpiring Princes: Much more of this Kind of pole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical Diſcourſe are We in this place, bordering on the ſeat of War, daily acquainted with: <hi>Onely by pride</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon</hi>) <hi>comes conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> The unſatiable deſire of being great and having much, makes all this ſtrife, from whence the miſery of mankind is grievous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aggravated; and in particular this part of the world involvd in a preſent labyrinth of trouble, and in danger of a future deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: the State whereof I shall endeavour with all modeſty, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor and indifferency to preſent to your view.</p>
            <p>Herein, <hi>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>,</hi> I shall give you the trouble of a short Relation of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:29767:8"/>the Source and Riſe of theſe Affairs, and ſo deſcend to theſe laſt times, which you will find to abound with all the abominable and horrid evills that can enter into the mind of Man to imagin: Which account of things, as a ſingle-hearted <hi>Hollander,</hi> I shall ſo manage, that all paſſion, Satyricall expreſſions, provocations, or offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive reflections shall be forborn; and all due obſervance manifeſted to all Soveraign Potentates, Princes and Powers whatſoever.</p>
            <p>In the Beginning of the Fifth Age (or Century) in the midſt of the diviſions of <hi>Rome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Meze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ray a French Author in his Abbrev. Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nolog. p. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> they ſpoke of the <hi>French,</hi> as of a barbarous people, perfidious, inconſtant and full of lies; they were enclined to warrs, having much wit and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, which gave them occaſion, courage and means to overthrow and ruin the <hi>Roman Empire in the Weſt:</hi> and upon thoſe ruins they meant, under their <hi>Clouis,</hi> to lay the foundation of a Kingdom that should be formidable to it's Neighbours, and that should have drawn along with it the reſt of <hi>Europe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Meze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ray pag. <hi>29.</hi>
               </note> under it's dominion: Which might haply have been, if it had not immediately been weakened by the dividing of it among his Children and Succeſſours; Who by their continuall debates ſo hindred, that it did not fall under One Monarchy; and by that means conſerved the Ballance ſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for the reſt of their Neighbours. But this good time endur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not longer than unto <hi>Charlemagne,</hi> who, having reunited thoſe ſo formidable forces of the <hi>French,</hi> and ſubdued the beſt part of <hi>Europe,</hi> was proclaimed <hi>Emperour</hi> by the <hi>Pope of Rome;</hi> and became <hi>the Arbiter of Chriſtendom.</hi> But, by a ſecret fatalitie, he fell into the ſame fault, which <hi>Clouis</hi> had committed with his Children,<note place="margin">Meze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ray pag. <hi>157.</hi>
               </note> and diſtributed this mighty <hi>Empire</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong his Children; ſo making an Eclyps in the <hi>Univerſal</hi> Monarchy; which <hi>the French</hi> at this day endeavour with ſo much zeal to retrieve. And indeed the Poſterity of <hi>Charle Magne</hi> have vexed themſelvs exceedingly about the reeſtablishing this <hi>grand Empire;</hi> though hitherto in vain; they at the laſt growing ſluggish, gave over, or however ſlacked much in that deſign:
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:29767:8"/>which gave occaſion that One of the <hi>Third Race</hi> came to be let upon the Throne; who reigns at preſent, more vigilant and more active than the Other of thoſe Branches do, who yet have ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver loſt their view and proſpect of the <hi>Monarchy of Clouis</hi> and <hi>of Charle Magne</hi> their Predeceſſours. But upon the advancement of <hi>Capet</hi> to the Crown, the Grandees of the Kingdom thought that He ought to ſuffer all things from them, becauſe they had put on his head the Diadem which he wore; whereupon they divided the Kingdom among them, and parted it into ſeverall pieces; which have not been reunited without great pains and trouble: and you muſt grant it me, that none at all, ſaving <hi>Lewis the Eleventh,</hi> was capable of effecting ſo great a work as the reuniting together of what was squandred abroad in ſo many Provinces; and ſo to bring his Kingdom into a State, not onely to defend himſelf againſt his Neighbours, but alſo to Rule over them; and to bring again to his Succeſſours the appetite and envy of reeſtablishing the Monarchy of <hi>Charle Magne;</hi> And this might have had a good iſſue by <hi>King Louis the</hi> XIV, if he had known how to purſue his victorie, in ſtead of ſtanding amuſed, at <hi>Seiſt</hi> near <hi>Utrecht</hi> in the year 1672.</p>
            <p>The high attempts of <hi>Louis the</hi> XI. put the following <hi>Kings of France</hi> again upon the oppreſſion of their people, and abaſing the greateſt Perſonages under them: And, the truth is, ſince <hi>the English</hi> were conſtrained to abandon the Kingdom of <hi>France,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mezeray pag. <hi>713.</hi>
               </note> more by their own quarrels and diviſions than by the valour of <hi>the French,</hi> their Kingdom hath received a wonderfull encreaſe and acceſs, by the reunion of their beſt Provinces; and their Monarchs have recalled to mind their ancient idea's and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions of <hi>the Univerſal Monarchy,</hi> and from time to time have ruined their Neighbours by warrs grounded upon their old pretences.</p>
            <p>And to take a little nearer inſpection into this affair, you moſt know, that when <hi>Louis the</hi> XI. did in the beginning of his Reign take notice, that his onely <hi>Brother Charles</hi> was allied with the <hi>Dukes of Burgondy</hi> and <hi>Britain</hi> againſt him, for the publick welfare
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:29767:9"/>of the <hi>Kingdom</hi> He carried ſmoothly toward them and made ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance as if he would give them contentment, but with intention to ſeparatethem, and to ruin them one after another; which did ſucceed very well to his mind, to the great dammage of the reſt of <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> and particularly to the deſtruction of <hi>the Netherlands:</hi> ſith that, ſince that time, <hi>the French</hi> have waſted <hi>Italy</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> and nigh ruined <hi>the Netherlands</hi> &amp;c. with the loſs of an innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable multitude of people and goods. And, in caſe the Civil Warrs for Religion had not prevented and diverted this fiery, impetuous, reſtleſs warlick humour, <hi>Poor Chriſtendom</hi> had ſeen itſelf at that very hour a Slave of <hi>France.</hi> Thence you have, <hi>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>,</hi> the generall ſource of the miſery of <hi>Europe, viz.</hi> the vaſt and unlimited ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that Sanguin Nation, their gall and unquiet humour, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to eat out and devour it's own bowels; if thoſe ancient preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces be not laid aſide: of which there is little hope, whilſt <hi>the French</hi> renew them every moment; ſtill wearying the world with thoſe chimerical images of their <hi>Louis</hi> and <hi>Charlemagne,</hi> which had ſufficiently galled the former ages; although they have been abolished by Solemn Treaties (yet become unſtuitfull) and by Praeſcription almoſt time out of mind. Lo the plague of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, and the true cauſe of all the calamities whereunder <hi>Europe</hi> at preſent groaneth.</p>
            <p>But to come to particulars: I shall not ſpeak here, but onely <hi>en paſſant,</hi> of the old Warrs of the <hi>Gauls</hi> againſt the <hi>Romans:</hi> nor tell how they brought to deſolation their <hi>Great Citie,</hi> as alſo a good part of <hi>Italie;</hi> nor how they ravaged in <hi>Aſia,</hi> and there eſtablished the Kingdom of <hi>Gallo-Graecia,</hi> as an evidence, as it ſeemeth, that this Climate always produced men given to high enterprizes above others, and to trouble the tranquillity of the world: For that this doth not ſo concern the <hi>French</hi> who have ſubdued the <hi>Gauls;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Meze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ray A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre v. Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nolog. p. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> and, by conſequence, are therefore the more to be feared; as likewiſe for their cruelty and natural furie, which they have inherited from their Anceſtours <hi>the Scythians;</hi> of whom <hi>their Authors</hi> make them Succeſſours.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:29767:9"/>
            <p>Onely pleaſe to conſult the <hi>Hiſtorians of Florence:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ouiccidrdin lib. <hi>1.</hi> della ſua Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria.</note> by whom you may ſee how they have troubled and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded the State of <hi>Italy,</hi> till almoſt the end of the four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth Century.</p>
            <p>Though true it is alſo, that among the <hi>Italians</hi> were ſeveral domeſtick and internall Warrs: yet they were without any cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty, without conſuming by fire, without the shedding of much humane bloud: as <hi>Machiavel,</hi> writing of a great battel that endured four hours together between many thouſands of men (I shall take heed of calling them Soldiers) of the <hi>Duke of Milains</hi> and of <hi>the Florentins,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Machiavel lib. <hi>5.</hi> del. Hiſt. p. <hi>175.</hi> &amp; <hi>216.</hi>
               </note> ſaith, that there was killed but one ſingle man, who fell off from his horſe, and was trampled under the feet of the Horſmen.</p>
            <q>Et in tanta rotta, &amp; in ſi lung a zutta, che durò dalle XX. alle XXIV. hore: non vi mori altri, che un huomo; il quale non diferite; ò d'altro virtuoſo colpo: ma caduto da cavallo, e calpeſto eſpiró, con tanta ſicurtà all' hora gli huomini comb attevano; &amp;c.</q>
            <p>In ſo much, that at that time in <hi>Italie</hi> properly there was neither peace nor watt.</p>
            <q>Perche pace non ſi può affermare cheſia; dove ſpeſſo i principati con l'armi l'uno el' altro s'aſſaltano, guerre ancora non ſi poſſono chia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mare; &amp;c.</q>
            <p>But after <hi>the French</hi> were entred there, and renewed their old pretences upon the Realms of <hi>Naples</hi> and <hi>Cicilie</hi> under <hi>Charles the</hi> VIII. this fair Elogie is given them by <hi>Guicciardin,</hi> that <hi>they filled the Countrey all over with fire and bloud:</hi> as he pathetically writes:</p>
            <q>Et che conduſſero ſeco in <hi>Italia;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Guicciardin Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teur Florentin, affectioné aux François; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me la pluſpart de ceux de ſa nation; dans ſon primier li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vre de l'Hiſt.</note> iſemi d'innumer abili ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamità; e d'horribiliſsimi accidenti, &amp; variatione di quaſi tutte le coſe: perche dalla paſſata ſua non ſolo hebbero princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pio mutationi di ſtato, ſoverſione di regni; e deſolationi di paeſi; &amp;c.</q>
            <p>And the <hi>ſame Authour</hi> remarketh the cauſe and originall of all thoſe miſeries and evils, by his following words; which I shall
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:29767:10"/>here inſert, becauſe they are worthy your reflection upon them:</p>
            <q>Mori finalmente Renato; e non havendo figliuoli maſchi, fece here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de in tuttigliſtati; eragioni ſue, <hi>Carlo</hi> figliuolo del Fratello, il quale morendo poco dipoi ſenza figliuoli, laſciò per teſtamento la ſua hereditá <hi>à Luigi XI. Re di Francia;</hi> a cui non ſolo ricadde; come à ſupremo Signore il <hi>Ducato d'Angiò;</hi> nel quale perche é membro della Corona; non ſuccedono le femine; ma con tutto: che'l <hi>Duca di Lorena</hi> aſſeriſſe appartenerſi a ſe la ſucceſsione de gli ſtati, entrò in poſſeſsione della <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venza;</hi> e poteva per vigore del Teſtamento medeſimo pretendere eſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gli applicate le ragioni: Che gli. <hi>Angioini</hi> havevano ſopra <hi>il Reame di Napoli;</hi> le quali eſſendo per la ſua morte, continuate in <hi>Carlo VIII.</hi> ſuo figliuolo, incommincio <hi>Ferdinando Re di Napoli</hi> ad havere poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſsimo auverſario, e ſi preſento grandiſsima opportunità a chiunque d'offenderlo deſiderava: perche <hi>il Regno di Francia</hi> er a in quel tempo piu Florido d'huomini: di gloria d'arme, d'arme, di potentia, di ric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chezze: e d'autorità intra gli altri regni: che forſe doppo <hi>Carlo Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi> fuſſe mai ſtato eſſendoſi ampliato novellamente, in ciaſcuna di quelle treparti; nelle quali appreſſo gli antichi ſi divideva tutta la <hi>Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia.</hi> Concioſia che non piu che quaranta anni à queſto tempo ſotto <hi>Carlo VII. Re,</hi> per molte vittorie ottenute con graviſsimi pericoli, chiamato bene auventurato, ſi fuſſero ridotto ſotto quelimperio, <hi>la Norman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia, e'l Ducato di Ghienna;</hi> provincie poſſedute primadagli <hi>Ingle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi:</hi> e ne gli ultimi anni di <hi>Luigi XI.</hi> la Contè a di <hi>Provenza, il Duca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to di Borgogna,</hi> e quaſi tutta <hi>la Picardia,</hi> dipoi aggiunto per nuovo matrimonio alla potentia di <hi>Carlo VIII, il Ducato di Bretagna;</hi> ne mancava nel animo di <hi>Carlo</hi> inclinatione à cercer d'acquiſtare con l'ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me <hi>il regno di Napoli,</hi> come giuſtamente appartenente a ſe, comin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciata per un certo inſtinto quaſi naturale inſino da pueritia; e nutrita dà conforti d'alcuni, che gli er ano molto accetti; i quali empiendolo di penſieri vani, gliproponevano, queſta eſſere occaſione d'avanzare la glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria de' Suoi predeceſſori: perche acquiſtato <hi>il Reame di Napoli,</hi> gli ſarebbe agevole, vincere <hi>l'Imperio de Turchi.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>Shortly after <hi>the ſaid Hiſtorian</hi> followeth his diſcourſe in this manner:</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:29767:10"/>
            <q>Incomminciò in tale diſpoſitione de gli animi, &amp; in tale confuſione delle coſe tanto inclinate à nuove perturbationi, <hi>l'Anno 1494,</hi> anno infeliciſsimo all <hi>'Italia,</hi> &amp; in verita <hi>anno primo</hi> de gli anni miſerabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bili perche aperſe la porta à innumerabili, &amp; horribili oalamità delle quali ſi può dire che per diverſi accidenti, habbia dipoi participato una gran parte del mondo, &amp; par les prodiges qui preſageoient cette guerre; d'incredibile timore ſi riempivano i popoli; ſpaventati gia per la Fama della potentia <hi>de Franceſi; &amp;c.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>And indeed <hi>King Charles the</hi> VIII. made himſelf Maſter of the Kingdom of <hi>Naples</hi> in few days, by the terrour of his Arms; (doing it by aſſault, burning the <hi>Mount S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Iohn,</hi> paſſing with his ſword through all that was to be found: an unheard of Caſe in thoſe times) and he ſoon loſt it again afterwards by his negligence, and too little care he had to preſerve it.</p>
            <p>But We muſt not now ſo flatter ourſelvs: <hi>Their preſent Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch</hi> know's no leſs how to conſerve than to conquer Provinces. If we do but obſerve the marches of this Imperious Nation on the borders of <hi>Germany,</hi> there we shall ſee <hi>Alſatia</hi> turned out of the hands of the <hi>Almains:</hi> and joyned to their Crown; a <hi>Duke of Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain</hi> driven out of his own Land; 3. <hi>Bishops,</hi> viz. <hi>Thoul, Metz</hi> and <hi>Verdun</hi> dismember'd from the <hi>Empire;</hi> which He Keeps in conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall diviſions and agitations by his Emiſſaries, by his intrigues and by his corruptions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> Deſcending to the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> the Principall Subject of our Diſcourſe: It is to be conſidered, in what manner <hi>the French</hi> have en deavoured to bring them into that miſerable Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition wherein we ſee them at this day; and to diſcover the true cauſe of their maladies: to this end We muſt have recourſe to the reign of <hi>Louis the XI. King of France,</hi> who by his ſubtilty and deceits ruined <hi>Charles the Stout Duke of Burgondy,</hi> and <hi>Lord of all the Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands;</hi> ſtirring him up new Enemies from time to time, who at laſt gathered together before <hi>Nancy;</hi> where he loſt his life, and his people all their welfare, which ſince that time they never could recover. Some years before, <hi>this Prince,</hi> who poſſed <hi>Bourgondy,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:29767:11"/>all the Netherlands,</hi> and (the <hi>Citie Paris</hi> being then a Frontier of the Kingdom of <hi>France</hi>) almoſt whole <hi>Picardy,</hi> did bridle, by his intelligence and courage, the ambition of this <hi>King</hi> ſo full of arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices: but, becauſe, for eaſing of his people, he was not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided with a good and well ordered Militia, he came to be ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized by the Other; who, by his horrible exactions of taxes and laying impoſitions upon his people, was always accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied and encompaſſed with a great quantity of armed men; the which gave him means and therewith deſire to extend his limits in deſpite of his Neighbours: but the matter was well enough bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanced untill the death of <hi>Charles the Stout:</hi> whoſe death cauſed to his people an abyſs of calamities and miſeries: ſeeing <hi>Louis the</hi> XI. at that time kept to himſelf <hi>Bourgondia,</hi> whole <hi>Piccardy, Arras,</hi> and many other conſiderable places: He likewiſe always amuſed <hi>the English,</hi> after the death of the ſaid <hi>Duke,</hi> to the end they should not hinder him in the conqueſts of thoſe Lands. Yet by the marriage of <hi>Mary of Bourgondy</hi> Heyreſs of the <hi>Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi> with <hi>Maximilian of Auſtria,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Philip. de Comines Chapit. ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond du. <hi>6.</hi> Livre.</note> as alſo by the loſs of the battel of <hi>Guinegate, the French</hi> could not execute their deſign, to bring under their power the <hi>Seventeen Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces;</hi> which yet they might very eaſily have joyned to their Crown,<note place="margin">The ſame Author. <hi>12.</hi> Chap. of the <hi>5.</hi> Book.</note> by a marriage of their <hi>Dauphine</hi> with the ſaid Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel <hi>Mary of Bourgondy:</hi> if the good God had not blinded <hi>Louis de</hi> XI. and taken away his ſenſes: and hereby was the way to the <hi>Univerſal Monarchy</hi> wonderfully made plain &amp; clear for <hi>Philip the Fair</hi> Son of <hi>Maximilian,</hi> and for <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les the Fifth:</hi> Then again the <hi>Netherlanders</hi> took a little breath; howbeit They were often incommodated by the invaſions of <hi>the French:</hi> who nevertheleſs found themſelvs not in poſture to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake any thing againſt their Neighbours, becauſe of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and leagues which ſoon after were formed in the boſom of that Kingdom: And yet, however hindred by ſo many cruel ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil warrs, <hi>the French</hi> quickly recovered again; and retook very much vigour by the courage and wiſe conduct of <hi>Henry the Great:</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:29767:11"/>The <hi>Netherlands</hi> having been in that intervall always rent by a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall warr in the bowells of their Provinces: but all that was not capable of ruining them: there was need of the engins of a <hi>Cardinal de Richelieu</hi> for an abſolute abaſing of them, and reeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tablishing the <hi>French</hi> in their ancient ſplendour, and making them (after the reduction of <hi>Rochel,</hi> and ſuppreſſing thoſe of the <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Religion</hi>) to follow on in the footſteps of their glorious An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtours, taking the way of <hi>Charlemagne</hi> unto the Monarchy: to which end they muſt throw down or debaſe the greatneſs of the <hi>Houſe of Auſtria,</hi> now prodigiouſly encreaſed, more by Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages than by Arms; which fell out exceeding well: He leaving behind him a worthy Succeſſour the <hi>Cardinal Mazarin</hi> for to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chieve the proſecution of his Deſigns; who would not have miſſed to emport <hi>the Netherlands;</hi> in caſe it had not then been prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the <hi>Queen of France Anna d' Auſtria,</hi> who did oblige him to make a marriage between the <hi>King Louis</hi> XIV. and the <hi>Infanta of Spain;</hi> and at the ſame time to conclude the peace of <hi>the Pire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nées;</hi> by which means the reſt of the then ſtaggering <hi>Netherlands</hi> was preſerved: then were affairs in a tolerable ſtate; whereof the good Subjects wished a long continuance and confirmation, having begun to taſt the ſweetneſs of the Peace: When yet in the year 1667, without any denunciation, or reaſonable cauſe of war, upon a weak cauſe, and pretext of a Cuſtom of Devolution of <hi>Fief</hi> upon the Children of the Firſt Marriage, practiſed in <hi>Brabant</hi> and other places in particular houſes, (which had never been confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Soveraign, nor uſed in Families of Princes) the <hi>French,</hi> as an effect of their enterprizing humour, inveſted the beſt Cities of thoſe Lands; the reſt whereof cannot maintain themſelvs other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than by miracles: But this deſervs a more particular Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The King Louis</hi> XIV. having conceived an unchangeable deſign of reaching hard for the Monarchy of the greateſt part of <hi>Europe,</hi> or, at leſt, to limit his Kingdom by <hi>the Alpes, the Pirenées,</hi> the <hi>Mediterranean Sea,</hi> the <hi>Ocean</hi> and the <hi>Rhine;</hi> judging that the <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlands,</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:29767:12"/>now in a ſtate of welfare and comlineſs, might ſerve for a wall of planks, for the further propagating of his Conqueſts, Did, in the Moneth of <hi>May</hi> in the year 1667. in time of a full peace, without any ſubject of rupture with <hi>Spain,</hi> and notwithſtanding good and poſitive aſſuranees of good correſpondence and friendship given by his Ambaſſadour at <hi>Madrid,</hi> march with an Army of 50000 men for to take poſſeſſion (ſo as they could, and not make war) of the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> devolved by the death of <hi>Philip the</hi> IV. <hi>King of Spain</hi> upon the <hi>Queen his Wife:</hi> and therewith He approached <hi>Charleroy,</hi> which the <hi>Spanjards</hi> had abandoned, becauſe it was not in a State of defence: But the <hi>French</hi> having in a short time brought it into a good poſture, ſoon after took, without great reſiſtance, the Towns of <hi>Tournay, Dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ay, Orchier, Liſle, Courtray, Audenard, Aeth, Bergen St. Winox,</hi> and <hi>Turnes,</hi> that is to ſay, all the beſt Cities of <hi>Flanders,</hi> ſituated in the boſom of the Land, which had very little or no Garriſons in them, becauſe of the aſſurance they had of a Peace, which had been ſo ſolemnly ſworn, and confirmed by a Marriage; which yet, in ſtead of ſerving as a band, as was hoped, for the nearer uniting of the two Crowns, was by <hi>the French</hi> made uſe of for a pretext of war: and by this means they were ſoon Maſters of three of the principall Rivers of the Land, <hi>viz.</hi> of the <hi>Liz,</hi> the <hi>Eſcarpes,</hi> and <hi>the Scheld;</hi> thereby breaking their Comerce and Communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with the remaining Towns, to their great decay of trade. And really <hi>the Spanjards</hi> being obliged by the <hi>Treaty of Aken</hi> to yield over to the <hi>French</hi> all that they took from them in the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> they became very unable to preſerve the reſt: For, as is evident, when we will paſs the Center within <hi>Bruxels,</hi> we cannot paſs the circumference of the Frontier for it's defence, otherwiſe than by three or four ſemidiameters which are very narrow, One whereof goeth by <hi>Mons</hi> (or <hi>Bergen</hi>) in <hi>Hainaut,</hi> (or <hi>Henegow</hi>) <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Gillain</hi> and <hi>Valencienne</hi> to <hi>Cambray;</hi> the Second by <hi>Namour</hi> (or <hi>Namen</hi>) to <hi>Luxemburgh;</hi> the Third by <hi>Gent</hi> and <hi>Ypre</hi> to <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Omer;</hi> the Laſt by <hi>Weert</hi> and <hi>Roermonde</hi> a village of <hi>Gelderland:</hi> all which
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:29767:12"/>paſſages are incommodated by the <hi>French,</hi> who, by their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual concourſes in thoſe parts, do very lightly hinder the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voys which should be brought into the Cities of the Frontiers. And who can, without tears in his eyes, look upon this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey that is ſo miſerably ſubjected to a cruel Contribution, (being not a fingers breadth of Land without vexation) the value whereof amounteth unto prodigious ſumms: the Citie of <hi>Maſtricht</hi> alone bringing up for their share four Millions: by which 'tis very eaſy to comprehend, That they purſue their Warrs at the charge of their Enemies; which doubtleſs they therefore deſire to continue, (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all their shows and expreſſions they make for Peace) and ſo will they make the poor people deſperate, who wish for nothing elſe but a good Peace and an end of the warrs, or a <hi>Maſter</hi> that is powerfull to defend them: and that they may be driven to that extremity I very much apprehend, and fear we shall shortly ſee effected; this having already been shewed in diverſe rencounters, particularly at <hi>Aire,</hi> (or <hi>Arien</hi>) where the Burgers did conſtrain the Garriſon which conſiſted of 400 men to give it over to the <hi>French.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is very true that the <hi>Netherlands</hi> are in a poor condition, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provided of all things; and that the <hi>King of Spain</hi> hath no more there than 6000 horſe to bring into the field, wherein their whole army conſiſteth, and 5000 <hi>Spanish</hi> foot to keep their Cittadels and places whereof they are moſt jealous; beſides about 15000 <hi>Waloons</hi> and <hi>Germans</hi> for the ordinary Garriſons of the Towns; which number is yet too little, and the Soldiers not well enough treated to be able to keep their places: in ſo much that <hi>the Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> are obliged to leave there more than ten thouſand men for their defence. My hairs riſe upon my head, when I conſider the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger wherein we are; and that the welfare of the Land depends onely upon the taking or ſurprizing of one or two Cities; the loſs whereof would undoubtedly cauſe the rendition of the reſt: for if the <hi>French</hi> take <hi>Bergen in Henegow,</hi> (where the Burgers are malcontent and murmure againſt the diſorders of the <hi>Spanish</hi>) <hi>Valencien</hi> and <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bray</hi> are cut off, and without ſuccour; having already much to do,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:29767:13"/>being blocked up by parties of the <hi>French</hi> Army, by <hi>Bouchain,</hi> and by a conſiderable Corps of the <hi>French</hi> that lodge in <hi>Cambreſis:</hi> And in caſe we looſe <hi>Namur,</hi> then the Citie and Land of <hi>Luxemburgh</hi> will immediately follow, for want of relief: ſo that one or two of thoſe Columns being taken out of the way, the reſt of the Building will fall of themſelvs, and applaud the triumph of the Overcomer. For the Great Cities, as <hi>Bruges, Gent, Bruxels,</hi> and <hi>Antwerp,</hi> either becauſe of their conformity in Religion with the <hi>Moſt Chriſtian King,</hi> or that they are in hopes (not without grounds) thereby to ſee the reflourishing of the Commerce, and to have their River <hi>Scheld</hi> opened, or that they apprehend that <hi>their Soveraign</hi> is too far off, or hath not ſtrength enough to guard them from the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultings of their Enemies who conſume them to their bones, will very lightly embrace the <hi>French</hi> yoke: for the multitude of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that are there chuſe ſuch Party as they will; which shall certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be the ſtrongeſt, and that is <hi>the French.</hi> There is no man now who diſcerns not the manifeſt danger of the <hi>Whole Netherlands,</hi> which are ſo drained out by theſe warrs, and among whom you rencounter many people that have not the greateſt affections for the <hi>Prince of Orange,</hi> and others, for reaſons too long here to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce, enclining to the <hi>French:</hi> Who then shall after this doubt, but that this <hi>French Monarch</hi> shall at laſt attain his aim, <hi>viz.</hi> firſt to extend his limits to <hi>the Alpes,</hi> to <hi>the Pirenées,</hi> and to <hi>the Rhine,</hi> and then to think further?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The French</hi> declare openly enough that they will not ſuffer <hi>the Spanish</hi> within the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> who during the minority of <hi>their King,</hi> or in their Civil Warrs, may give any trouble to this great and mighty Kingdom. Men muſt reform this errour which till now hath prevailed in their Opinions, That the <hi>Prince of Orange,</hi> joyning his troops with thoſe of <hi>Spain,</hi> should be able to ſave the <hi>Netherlands:</hi> the contrarie having been experienced; for, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding what efforts he uſed, the <hi>French</hi> this laſt year took <hi>Condé, Bouchain</hi> and <hi>Aire;</hi> being three places which mightily incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modate the Other; the laſt whereof had more than 200000 livres
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:29767:13"/>of contribution of <hi>France.</hi> Further is to be conſider'd the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages they have over us by their Magazins, which make them ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in the Camp with their numerous Cavalry, when their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies cannot shew themſelvs for want of forrage: by which means they have the opportunity to make ſiege by ſome detachement, oppoſing the body of their Army (which is ſtronger in Cavalry than the Army of <hi>the Allies</hi>) in ſome advantagious place againſt thoſe who would bring ſuccour to the place they beſiege; and ſo they play ſure play, not hazarding their reputation and glory. The King came in at the beginning of the Spring (when there was no graſs on the field to feed the horſes) with an Army of 20000 horſe and 30000 foot, leaving a few men within the Cittadels, now almoſt impregnable, which he had cauſed to be built, (after the peace made at <hi>Aken</hi>) at <hi>Liſle, Tournay, Arras, Dunkerk,</hi> and other places; and drawing out all the Garriſons which make up 30000 men, he joyned them to the troops of the Kings houſe, who were 16000 men ſtrong: whereas on the contrary, the <hi>Prince of Orange</hi> was neceſſitated to weaken his Army, and to ſend or leave more than ten thouſand men in the greateſt Cities (for fear they should render themſelvs) then muſt he have an artillerie well furnished, regulated and governed, for to open the Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paign to ſome conqueſts, the <hi>Germans</hi> being ſtill conſtrained to ſtay in their winter-quarters, uncapable to act or cauſe any di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, through defect of forrage in the <hi>Netherlands.</hi> Then after an enterprize don upon any place, as is ordinary, <hi>His Majeſtie</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>returns back, <hi>re benè geſtâ,</hi> and without any hazard of a battel; then makes detachements from <hi>Flanders</hi> to <hi>Germany,</hi> and ſo illudeth the great deſigns of <hi>the Allies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We conclude then by all this, that the irregular ambition of the <hi>French,</hi> their unſatiable avarice, their old pretences upon <hi>quaſi</hi> all the Provinces of <hi>Europe,</hi> their will and inclination to robbery, their vain, inconſtant and unquiet humour not permitting their Neighbours to live in reſt, are the true cauſes of all the calamities and miſeries of <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> and eſpecially of the <hi>Netherlands;</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:29767:14"/>whom, it ſeems God had placed, as in his anger, in the midſt of <hi>Europe,</hi> to the end they might be the beam of the Ballance.</p>
            <p>Now in this caſe, It is neceſſary to have recourſe to other Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, under God, than thoſe which to this time have been uſed, for the healing us of this <hi>French</hi> Diſeaſe, that cometh now to the Noble parts of the Body of the <hi>Seventeen Provinces,</hi> making them rotten, and fall off by pieces, being in danger of a total deſtruction: Better means know we not than the application of <hi>English Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> to make the Enemies ſalivate and evacuate what they have with ſo great greedineſs ſwallowed in. For whither elſe shall we betake ourſelvs for refuge, but to the <hi>English,</hi> for reeſtablishing the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpois ſo neceſſary for the publick reſt and felicity of <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> and eſpecially of the <hi>Netherlands?</hi> for whoſe Conſervation <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> is ſo greatly in it's intereſt concerned, having alſo received of God the advantage of a ſituation ſo excellent, as to be fit to keep the ballance of <hi>Europe,</hi> and be an Arbiter of all things there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, shewing in effect that it hath reaſon on all occaſions to ſay, <hi>Cui adhaerco, ille praeeſt, Whom I incline to shall prevail.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And truly it is a glory for the <hi>King of England,</hi> that, whilſt O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther people are very unable to help, or are menaced, and ſo in an appreehenſion of the terrible forces of the <hi>King of France,</hi> or are overcome by his preſents, againſt their own intereſt, or elſely ſtill in a deep lethargy, He alone can praeſcribe limits to the, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt endleſs, ambition of the <hi>French,</hi> to bring them to reaſon, and put them in mind that they with their Monarchy, now ſo idoliz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the deſigns whereof they believe to be infallible, are yet no other than men, and ſubject to change of fortune; which would enſue, in caſe the <hi>English</hi> should take the party of the <hi>Allies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And what help can there be expected if we caſt our eyes on o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places for relief? Let's begin with <hi>the Alpes;</hi> there we have an object of aſtonishment, in obſerving the Low-ſpiritedneſs of the <hi>Switſers,</hi> that mercenary people, obliged by reaſon of State and formal Treaties to the guarrantie of the <hi>Dukedom of Milain</hi> and the <hi>French County;</hi> which yet they ſuffered, not long ſince, to be
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:29767:14"/>taken, in their ſight. If we come to <hi>Turin,</hi> there we shall find a <hi>Duke de Savoy</hi> under the government of a <hi>French Mother,</hi> and depending on intelligences from the <hi>French Court,</hi> and in ſome ſort bridled by the Fort of <hi>Pignarol,</hi> which is the Key of his Land. Not far from thence shall we find thoſe of <hi>Geneva</hi> irreſolved, trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling for fear, prepared to ſuffer inſultings, and to make all ſorts of curteous addreſſes for preſerving their quiet; the conqueſt of whom would but be as the fruit of one <hi>Campagne,</hi> or, it may be, of three months time. If we enter further into <hi>Italie,</hi> there we shall find <hi>Princes</hi> weak and timid, who will not oppoſe themſelvs againſt the progreſſes of the victorious arms of <hi>France,</hi> unleſs in the greateſt extremitie. The <hi>Republick</hi> of <hi>Venice,</hi> in former times called <hi>the Buckler of Italie,</hi> being newly delivered from a grievous war againſt the <hi>Turks,</hi> shall not engage, or but very ſlowly, and putting off ſo long as they can, in a new war againſt <hi>France,</hi> which might be worse to them than the former. I shall not here mention <hi>the Pope,</hi> nor the Great <hi>Duke of Tuſcany,</hi> who shall never under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take any thing of themſelvs, unleſs what properly relates to the reading of their Breviarie; or, at beſt, they may be good to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trive a Treaty, or to fortifie one that is already made by Others. If we paſs into <hi>Poland</hi> and <hi>Portugal,</hi> we shall ſtand admiring, as we might not long ſince have don, in <hi>Savoy</hi> and <hi>Bavaria,</hi> to ſee the <hi>Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſſes</hi> to be <hi>French Wives,</hi> who poſſeſs and govern their Husbands, kept by the <hi>French,</hi> and driven by the ſame ſpirit of ambition to endeavour <hi>that Kings</hi> greatneſs, and who perſwade themſelvs, that they have don a ſingular favour to <hi>the Allies,</hi> that they have till this timeforborn to give them ſome notable diverſion; which we have reaſon to apprehend for the future.</p>
            <p>In ſo much that there is none but his <hi>Majeſtie of Great Britain,</hi> that is capable and worthy to ſuſtain the quality and heavy (though glorious) burden of Arbiter and Peacemaker of the troubled world: for we shall here leave out, as unworthy to be <hi>Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours,</hi> the <hi>Swedes,</hi> thoſe mercenary Souls and boutefeus of <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> thoſe infortunate Braves, who in ſtead of procuring the peace
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:29767:15"/>and reſt of the <hi>Empire,</hi> where of they were Conſiderable Members, have diſturbed the tranquility thereof, by their unjuſt invaſion in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lands of an <hi>Elector,</hi> then employed on the Frontiers for the common defence of his Countrey; having ſold themſelvs to <hi>France,</hi> for finishing the combuſtion of the reſt of <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> There is therefore no other that can ſuſtain the rank and do the function of a true <hi>Eſculapius</hi> to heal our ſickneſſes, by Others incurable, but the <hi>King of England,</hi> and that by preſcribing to the <hi>French</hi> ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of peace as shall reduce them from beyond the River <hi>the Somme,</hi> to keep within their old limits, as in the time of <hi>Louis</hi> XI. in the beginning of his Reign. And in caſe they refuſe it, there is none but the <hi>King of England</hi> that can make them ſwallow Ellebore to purge their brains of thoſe ill humours and fumeswhich cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt them, and blot out of their corrupted imaginations the vaſt idea's and Chimaera's of their <hi>Charlemagne;</hi> and ſo to calm all the troubles and tempeſts of <hi>Europe,</hi> whereof they are the Cauſe.</p>
            <p>His Majeſty shall but follow therein the footſteps of his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Anceſtors, who paſſed beyond the Seas with numerous Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to reliev the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> and not ſuffer them to fall into the hands of the <hi>French,</hi> believing that whole <hi>England</hi> should be in great danger of deſtruction,<note place="margin">Phil. de Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines chap. <hi>1.</hi> l. <hi>4.</hi> &amp; <hi>8.</hi> chap. of l. <hi>3.</hi> of his memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rialls.</note> in caſe ſo many Soveraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties were joyned with that Crown: This matter should be wonderfully taken to heart: Witneſs <hi>Philip de Comi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</hi> And there is no doubt but the <hi>English</hi> people would liberally contribute to that undertaking, after their old cuſtom, yea, were it to carry an Army into <hi>France:</hi> as <hi>King Edward</hi> did, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring <hi>King Louis</hi> XI. to render him the Kingdom of <hi>France,</hi> that was his own, that he might redreſs the State of the Religion and the Nobles, and reſtore to the people their old Liberties, and take off the great charge and vexation under which they groaned.<note place="margin">Comines chap. <hi>5.</hi> of lib. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> I wonder very much, that the like deſign was not formed two years ago, when the Inhabitants of <hi>Ghienne</hi> and <hi>Bretagne</hi> ſtretched out their arms to <hi>England,</hi> for to taſt, under the conduct of the <hi>Duke of York</hi> or <hi>Monmouth</hi> the ſweetneſs of an
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:29767:15"/>
               <hi>English</hi> Government, which they wish for unto this day.</p>
            <p>Do the <hi>English</hi> want Motives to excite them hereunto? I beſeech you, what shall, after ſuch <hi>French</hi> Conqueſts, become of the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish</hi> Commerce? is not that ſufficiently ruined, or lamentably decayed already? The <hi>Hamburgh-trade</hi> is, upon the matter, quite loſt, as to the <hi>English</hi> manufactures, which in times of peace were ſold into <hi>Germany, Pomerania,</hi> and other adjacent Countreys: and ſo alſo is the <hi>Dort-trade</hi> loſt, by which the <hi>Spanish Netherlands,</hi> and the parts of Germany, which ly that way, were wont to be ſupplyed with <hi>English</hi> Cloath: by reaſon whereof thoſe <hi>English</hi> Manufactures, as Cloath, Serges, Bayes, &amp;c. which formerly gave 50. per piece, are now ſold for 35. or 37. at the higheſt; which proves ſo great an evil to <hi>England,</hi> that thoſe Cloathiers, which formerly employed 400 perſons at work, have not now work for 20 perſons; which hath cauſed the price of Wool to fall 40. per Cent cheaper than heretofore: and the people are forced to ſteal it out of <hi>England,</hi> and ſell it to the <hi>French,</hi> who with the ſame make Serges and other Stuffs, to the dammage and utter loſs of the <hi>English</hi> trade: The complaints of this kind are every where heard; as alſo of that palpable cauſe of this decay in Commerce, from the taking, roving, plundering, confiſcating of ſo many <hi>English</hi> ships by the <hi>French</hi> within a short time; the Value whereof with their Loadings is inaeſtimable, and thereupon the provoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and grievances unſufferable.</p>
            <p>But above all, the <hi>English</hi> ought to caſt their eyes upon, and provide a remedy for the great ſtrength and encreaſe of the <hi>French</hi> Ships, which trouble all Navigation at preſent; and what shall they do, when they shall come to diſpoſe <hi>(Deus avertat omen, God forbid it)</hi> of the Navall Forces of <hi>Holland,</hi> and of their riches in <hi>the Indies?</hi> And more particularly is to be conſidered what shall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of the <hi>English</hi> Traffick in the <hi>Mediterranean Sea:</hi> There is no Merchant that know's not how abſolutely neceſſary the <hi>English</hi> Trade is with <hi>Spain,</hi> as alſo with <hi>Smyrna,</hi> and all thoſe parts to which we muſt paſs through thoſe <hi>Mid-land Seas:</hi> but how can
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:29767:16"/>that be maintaind, if the <hi>French</hi> ſhould make a Conqueſt of <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilia, Naples</hi> and <hi>Sardinia?</hi> Let but in ſpection be made into their proceedings at <hi>Meſsina;</hi> where, beſides what they have gained at Land, they have now at Sea 25. Galleys, and 50. great veſſels, menof war, and a great number of others leſs, but very commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious for tranſport of Soldiers and proviſions; they being abſolute Maſters and Dominators in thoſe Seas: whereto gives no ſmall ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage the Commodity of their Ports of <hi>Marſeilles</hi> and <hi>Toulon,</hi> which are not far diſtant; from whence ſuccours and proviſions may be ſent to refresh them in <hi>Meſsina</hi> in leſs than eight days time: and, by conſequence, they may ſoon be Maſters of thoſe <hi>Islands,</hi> and afterwards of the Kingdom of <hi>Napels:</hi> for the Faction of <hi>Anjou</hi> (that is, of <hi>France</hi>) is not all extinguished there: and then can the <hi>French,</hi> when they will, ruin the navigation of the <hi>Northern</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants, who have there neither Ports nor Galleys; which are two things very neceſſary in thoſe Seas, becauſe of the great Calms which in Summer time are often met with there. Theſe Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, with many more, call aloud to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation to awaken, and help themſelvs and us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For a Concluſion:</hi> I propoſe two particular ways for the further engaging of <hi>England</hi> to come into our help:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> that a true and firm Union may be cemented between <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> the Expedient of the ſo much diſcourſed of <hi>Marriage</hi> between Our <hi>Prince of Orange</hi> and <hi>Madam Maria,</hi> daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the <hi>Duke of York</hi> ought to be endeavoured that it may ſpeedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be effected: <hi>His Highneſs</hi> ought to ſollicite it with ardour and paſſion: after the Example of <hi>Charles the Stout, Duke of Bourgondy,</hi> and <hi>Lord of the Netherlands,</hi> who married the Siſter of <hi>King Edward</hi> of the <hi>Houſe of York,</hi> for to fortifie himſelf againſt <hi>King Louis</hi> XI. (who had got advantage againſt him ſo much by ſurpriz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es and deceits in time of peace,<note place="margin">Phil. de Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines Chap. <hi>XI.</hi> lib. <hi>3.</hi> of his Memor.</note> like as our <hi>Frenchmen</hi> did in the year 1667.) for otherwiſe he would never have don it, for the great love he bore to <hi>the Houſe of Lancaſter</hi> whereof he was a near Relation by his Mothers ſide.
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:29767:16"/>If therefore ſo great a Prince, that followed rather the incite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of his anger, than of reaſon, ſacrificed the intereſt of his Houſe to the publick welfare: what ſhall not Our Illuſtrious <hi>Prince,</hi> who is ſo wiſe and Politique, do to attain that deſign or end ſo neceſſarie for the ſaving of <hi>the Netherlands?</hi> unto the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation whereof that of <hi>England</hi> is in ſeparably annexed. For in caſe the <hi>French</hi> ſhould now become Maſters of the <hi>Spanish Netherlands,</hi> will it not follow then that <hi>Holland</hi> and the other <hi>United Provinces</hi> ſhall be conſtrained at laſt to take upon them the ſame yoke? and ſuppoſe <hi>the Hollanders</hi> could maintain themſelvs with ſome aſſiſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce from <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> yet would they not be always the continual Theater and ſeat of war; but rather at laſt ſubmit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelvs to the great and mighty <hi>King of France,</hi> in hopes to enjoy, without fear of any Enemy, a perfect tranquility and long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing Reſt. A preſent hearty Conjunction between <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Us</hi> therefore is the preſent needfull; to which the foreſaid Marriage ſeems to be a proper medium: for the accomplishing whereof the bleſſing of the Almighty is earneſtly implored, that he, who ſtraitneth and enlargeth Kings, Kingsdoms, and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths, that limits the Grandees of the Earth, putting a hook in their noſtrils, that maketh warrs to ceaſe on the earth, and ſetteth up the oppreſſed and the lowly, will, if it may ſtand with his good pleaſure, make this marriage of our great <hi>Prince</hi> with that Illus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trious <hi>Princeſs Mary</hi> to become ſucceſsfull for thoſe righteous and happy ends: that not onely by this great knot the hearts of thoſe two Grand perſonages may be more united; but alſo that the Two Nations may concur and conſpire with more harmonie, courage, and activitie, to procure a good peace for the reſt and tranquilitie of <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> and particularly of <hi>England</hi> and the <hi>Netherlands;</hi> a peace, I mean, not coloured over, nor plaiſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ſuch as the <hi>French</hi> (when <hi>the Allies</hi> shall be disarmed and ſeparated) shall preſently break, and ſo again ſurprize the <hi>Netherlands;</hi> who indeed ought to be always in poſture of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence; and who (when the ballance shall be kept equall in <hi>Europe</hi>)
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:29767:17"/>ought to ſerve for a bank and barr againſt the inundations and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts of this unquiet and imperious Nation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> As to a ſure <hi>Aſylum,</hi> under our Almighty Protector, We would addreſs to the Renowned <hi>Parliament of England,</hi> now beginning their <hi>Seſsion:</hi> Upon them are at preſent the eyes of all the Conſiderable and Conſidering Parties of <hi>Europe:</hi> Ill men are jealous and conceive fears concerning them; Good men hope for great advantages from their grave and wiſe Councels: The loud clamours of the innumerable injuries don by the <hi>French</hi> to the honeſt Subjects of <hi>England</hi> in their Commerce, more ways than one, to their ineſtimable dammage, we know, have reached their ears: and the ſad ſtate of theſe Lands, with all the preſent evils and future dangers I have mention'd in <hi>this Letter</hi> cannot be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known to them: the Sympathy of their affections with our miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and the identity of their Cauſe with Ours, will, we hope, effect ſo much, that Their Wisdoms will propoſe, vote, direct, order, and conclude of ſuch ways and means whereby the ſober Inhabitants, and particularly the Trading Party of <hi>England,</hi> may with <hi>Us</hi> be extricated out of this Labyrinth in which we are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wilder'd; that at laſt we may arrive at ſuch a ſtate of juſt freedom and ſafety, as may excite us, with them, to render to the God of wonders hearty praiſe and thanksgiving for his wonderfull deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verances and preſervations: for which you have the concurrent Vote of</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>,</salute> 
               <signed>Yours &amp;c.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
